Finding Aid for Austin Blair Family Papers 1849-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Austin Blair Family Papers 1849-1981, 1895-1920
Blair family.
1 oversize folder UAm
3.5 linear feet
Materials collected by Helen Blair Lamar and subsequently donated to the Blair Society for Genealogical Research and pertaining to the Austin Blair family of Michigan and related family lines, the Hanks family and the North family. The collection, arranged by family name and then by individual, includes original with some typed transcripts of family letters, diaries, legal documents, poetry, personal items, and visual materials.
9615 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library by the Blair Society for Genealogical Research (Donor No. 8404 ) in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
The Blair family is one of the more notable families of Michigan. The compiler of this collection of papers, Helen Marie Blair Lamar (1898-1981), was the daughter of Charles A. Blair (1854-1912), who served as attorney general and justice of the Supreme Court of Michigan, and granddaughter of Austin Blair (1818-1894), the governor of Michigan during the Civil War.
Austin Blair was born in Caroline, New York and moved to Jackson, Michigan in 1841 to practice law. He took an active part in the formation of the Republican Party "under the oaks" of Jackson in 1854 and became increasingly more involved in politics, serving as governor and then as congressman.
George H. Blair, the eldest of Austin's sons, had a difficult life. He had trouble holding a job and worked off and on for the United States Postal Service. He married Vienna Peck in 1878 and they had three children. George accidentally shot his son Charles Austin's arm off while cleaning his gun. In 1897 Vienna divorced him after he committed adultery with Josephine Darrell. His brother Charles intervened, making him leave his mistress and go down to Florida, where the Blair brothers had bought some land. In 1901 he was paralyzed and returned to his brother Charles' house in Jackson, where he spent the last three years of his life as an invalid.
Charles Austin Blair, the second of Austin and Sarah Blair's four sons, graduated from the University of Michigan in 1876 and later was a member of the Board of Regents, as was his father. He was the responsible brother, often helping his less steady brothers get jobs, and giving them substantial financial support. He married Effie Caroline North (1861-1944) in 1879 and they had four children. Effie's parents were Guy Franklin North (1832-1890), trumpeter of the 18th Michigan Infantry, Company B, during the Civil War, and Ella Aurelia Hanks North Cole (1837-1917).
Two of Charles and Effie Blair's four children survived childhood. George Fred Blair (1880-1955) graduated from Annapolis and spent several years in the navy before trying his hand at various unsuccessful business ventures. He married Lucie Chamberlain, the daughter of Oregon Governor and Senator George Chamberlain, and had five children. Helen Marie Blair Lamar (1898-1981), known as "Peachie," went to Gunston Hall School in Washington, D.C. and then to St. Mary's Academy and College in Portland, Oregon. She married George "Jack" Lamar in 1921.
Austin Blair's other two sons were Frederick Johnson Blair (1860-1943) and Austin True Blair (1864-1944). Fred married four times, once to a second cousin. He ended up in Washington D.C., working for the government, after a stint spent attempting to grow pineapples in Florida. Austin True was an actor in New York. He seemed to write brother Charles the most persistent appeals for financial assistance, for work was often scarce and he had a chronic gambling problem.
Helen Blair Lamar kept the papers of the Blair, Hanks and North families for many years. After her death they were given to the Blair Society for Genealogical Research, which in turn donated them to the Bentley Historical Library. This collection exemplifies the slightly random character of family papers accumulated over several generations. There is a wide variety of material on a large number of individuals. In an attempt to keep things as clear as possible, the majority of the papers--manuscript, typescript and printed--have been arranged by FAMILY GROUPS which are subdivided by Personal Name and arranged by generation. This is followed by a small second series of miscellaneous PRINTED MATERIALS. A substantial third series of VISUAL MATERIALS includes Scrapbooks, Photographs, Daguerreotypes and Ambrotypes, Tintypes and Glass Plate Negatives.
Subjects:
Blair family.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Blair Society for Genealogical Research.; Blair, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1854-1912.; Blair, Effie.; Florida--History.; Hanks family.; Jackson (Mich.); Judges' spouses--Michigan--Jackson.; North family.; Pineapple industry--Florida.; Women--Michigan--Jackson.; Wyoming--History.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Blair family.; Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Blair Society for Genealogical Research.; Blair, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1854-1912.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; Hanks family.; North family.; Portage Lake (Jackson County, Mich.); Pineapple industry--Florida.
Genre/Form:
Ambrotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Diaries.; Glass negatives.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Family Groups
  The first series, comprised of manuscript material, some printed material and some unique items, including handpainted silk and locks of hair from children who died young, is arranged by Family Groups. Helen Blair Lamar created typed transcriptions of much of the correspondence of her parents, Charles Austin and Effie North Blair. She apparently discarded a significant amount of original material, for a note written to her niece Betty Blair Grandstaff in 1958 reads, "I am discarding more boxes full of letters."
  As a result, the majority of the correspondence of the collection is in the non-original format of three typescript volumes entitled "Life of Charles A. Blair," volumes 1 and 2, and "Letters of Effie C. Blair." Much of Charles Blair's correspondence is with his three brothers, and spans over 35 years. As adults, the brothers often relied on Charles for support and utilized a variety of tactics, from cajoling to threatening, to extract favors and funds from him. The first volume includes brother George Blair's colorful accounts from Wyoming, where he was prospecting for gold in 1876.
  The volume of letters from Effie to her daughter Helen spans a 20 year period, from 1924 until Effie's death in 1944. These informative letters are packed with meticulous descriptions of Effie's daily life. This volume also includes early letters to Helen from her Gunston Hall School chums. All three volumes include transcriptions of newspaper articles and other materials in addition to correspondence.
  There are also a few noteworthy letters that have survived in the original. Guy North wrote a fascinating letter to his new wife Ella Hanks North on the eve of his enlistment in the Civil War. Lot V. North (1806-1900), Guy's father, struck up a correspondence with his granddaughter Effie North Blair late in his life and writes at great length about his religious views. There are two letters written in 1895 by Hattie Rea to her sister Alice, second wife of Frederick Johnson Blair (1860-1943). Hattie details what the newlyweds will need when they join her in the wilds of Florida. Both Fred and George Blair, with the financial support of brother Charles, unsuccessfully attempted to start pineapple plantations on the St. Lucie River in Florida. There is also a smattering of original family letters, business correspondence and greeting cards. Typed transcriptions are noted; otherwise, assume the item is in its original manuscript format.
  The collection includes two journals kept by Ella Hanks North Cole (1837-1917), spanning the years from 1890 to 1906. She played the organ for several churches in Toledo, Ohio and then in Jackson, Michigan, where she lived with her daughter Effie North Blair's family. Due to financial difficulties, Ella was unable to stay with her second husband, Myron Cole, who was dying of cancer of the face back in Toledo. After his death, Ella remained with her daughter until her own death in 1917. The journals detail her health, money troubles, attendance at church functions and ambivalence about card playing.
  Another set of writings in this collection are a series of newspaper articles about "Historic Jackson County" and some unpublished short stories by Nellie Blair Greene (1882-1953). She was Helen Blair Lamar's cousin, and later married her cousin Harriet's widower and wrote for wrestling magazines.
  There is a wide variety of official documents and printed items, including wedding certificates, deeds and invitations to important events. Most of these materials are in the first series, within the subseries of the person to whom they relate.
  Information about the Blair, Hanks, North and related families is in evidence throughout this collection. There are, as well, several folders of specifically genealogical material, including notes, Daughters of the American Revolution applications and acid-free copies of newspaper clippings. These are filed in the Helen Blair Lamar subseries, for she apparently generated the majority of this material. A large Blair Family tree is housed in the oversize folder. A number of family group charts, supplied by the processor, have been added to the very beginning of the collection, along with other background materials, in order to help the researcher grasp the genealogy. They are accurate to the best of her knowledge.
  - First Generation
    - Cyrus D. Hanks (1812-1890)
      - Cemetery deed 1875 (Box 1)
      - Estate papers 1895-1901 (Box 1)
    - Caroline Colbleigh Hanks (1820-1901)
      - Handpainted floral arrangements on silk and lacework (Box 1)
    - Lot V. North (1806-1900)
      - Letter to his sister Lucy North, and niece Mabel 1893, A.L.S. and typed transcript (Box 1)
      - Letters to his granddaughter Effie North Blair 1893-1897, undated, 4 folders; 12 A.L.S. and typed transcripts (Box 1)
  - Second Generation
    - Guy Franklin North (1832-1890)
      - Marriage certificate to Ella Aurelia Hanks 1860 (Box 1)
      - Letter to his wife, Ella Hanks North 1861, A.L.S. and typed transcript (Box 1)
    - Ella Aurelia Hanks North Cole (1837-1917)
      - Copybook with genealogical data 1873 (Box 1)
      - Private Journal 1890-1898, 1906 (Box 1)
      - Diary, 1901-1905 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence and verse 1849-1894, undated (Box 1)
      - Inventory of possessions undated (Box 1)
    - Jane E. North Davis
      - "Birthday Tribute" written by Jane, Ella Hanks North's sister-in-law, to her husband 1861 (Box 1)
    - Austin Blair (1818-1894)
      - Marriage certificate to Sarah Louise Horton Ford 1849 (Box 1)
      - Letters to Austin and Sarah Blair 1861-1895 (Box 1)
      - Invitation to dinner at the White House from President and Mrs. Johnson 1867 (Box 1)
      - Invitation to reception at the Japanese Embassy 1872 (Box 1)
      - Handwritten copy of will 1894 (Box 1)
      - Posthumous inventory of valuable papers undated (Box 1)
      - Invitation to and programs for unveiling of Austin Blair statue 1898 (Box 1)
      - Address by John Patton delivered at unveiling of Austin Blair statue 1898 (Box 1)
  - Third Generation
    - Charles A. Blair (1854-1912)
      - "Life of Charles A. Blair," volumes 1 & 2., 2 folders (Box 1)
        (Typed transcription of letters written to Charles and newspaper clippings, compiled by his daughter, Helen Blair Lamar)
      - Letters to Charles A. Blair from his brothers and their children 1894-1904, undated (Box 1)
      - Business Correspondence 1900-1904 (Box 1)
      - Poem inviting Charles A. Blair to William Palmer and Charles Townsend's joint birthday party 1899 (Box 1)
      - Invitations 1904 (Box 1)
      - Deeds of Charles A. Blair and his brothers 1885-1903 (Box 1)
      - Financial statements and receipts 1885-1904 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous notes, probably transcribed by Helen Blair Lamar undated (Box 1)
    - Effie Caroline North Blair (1861-1944)
      - "Letters of Effie C. Blair" (Box 1)
        (Typed transcription compiled by her daughter, Helen Blair Lamar)
      - Letter to her husband, Charles A. Blair 1883, A.L.S. and typed transcription (Box 1)
      - Letters to Effie C. Blair 1909-1922 (Box 1)
      - Letters and greeting cards to Effie C. Blair 1930-1944 (Box 1)
      - Letter informing Effie C. Blair of the death of her grandfather, Lot. V. North 1900, A.L.S. and typed transcript (Box 1)
      - Unofficial will 1919 (Box 1)
      - Rubbing of Effie C. Blair's tombstone circa 1944 (Box 1)
    - Alice Rea Blair
      (second wife of Frederick Johnson Blair (1860-1943), married 1895)
      - Letters from her sister Hattie concerning move to Florida 1895 (Box 1)
  - Fourth Generation
    - George Fred Blair (1880-1955)
      - Letters to his father, Charles A. Blair 1905-1912 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous material 1895-1920, undated (Box 1)
      - Compilation of poems by Lucie Chamberlain Blair (1883-1973), his wife 1973 (Box 1)
      - Wedding announcements for two of his daughters 1925, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Ella Louise Blair (1882-1886) and Walter Guy Blair (1884-1886)
      - Locks of hair 1886 (Box 1)
    - Helen Marie Blair Lamar (1898-1981)
      - Writings, including two accounts of trips to Florida 1930-1961, undated (Box 1)
      - Letters to Helen Marie Blair 1912-1919, undated (Box 1)
      - Letters to Helen Marie Blair Lamar 1921-1973 (Box 1)
      - Sympathy notes after the death of her mother, Effie C. Blair 1944 (Box 1)
      - Financial statements 1917-1920 (Box 2)
      - Will 1960 (Box 2)
      - Death certificate 1981 (Box 2)
      - Gunston Hall School memorabilia 1912-1926, undated (Box 2)
      - Memorabilia 1872-1958, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Genealogical materials and newspaper clippings she compiled, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Nellie Blair Greene (1882-1953) (daughter of Frederick J. Blair and his second cousin Mary Eliza "Katharine" Horton)
      - Writings (Box 2)
      - Newspaper articles about Jackson, MI 1929 (Box 2)
      - "The Luck of Juan Largo" 1950 (Box 2)
      - "The Pearl Dragon" undated (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous short stories undated (Box 2)
- Printed Materials
  The Printed Materials series is comprised of the few items that cannot be so obviously linked to a specific member of the family, e.g., the official program of the Jackson Centennial, held in 1929.
  - Banquet Programs 1891-1904 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1897-1912 (Box 2)
  - Class Day Exercises 1873-1878 (Box 2)
  - B.P.O. Elks 1902-1904 (Box 2)
  - "Governors of the Territory and State of Michigan" 1928 (Box 2)
  - Jackson, Michigan Centennial, official program 1929 (Box 2)
  - "The Searchlight", includes a paper by Charles A. Blair 1902 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1872-1920, undated (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The manuscript and printed materials are complemented by the large collection of Visual Materials (Boxes 2-4 and oversize folder). Helen Blair made at least one of the scrapbooks, "Old Homes," a recollection of her early life in Jackson, Michigan. This has been photocopied onto acid-free paper. Other scrapbooks, comprised of photographs, often with captions, and newspaper clippings, had been unbound and the original order is uncertain. There are five generations represented in the visual materials and most of the people and places in the photographs, glass plate negatives, tintypes, daguerreotypes and ambrotypes have been identified; some have been dated. Places, particularly the Austin Blair house in Jackson, the Blair's summer place on Portage Lake, and the pineapple plantations in Florida are well documented. This series provides a rich visual context in which to read the textual materials.
  - Scrapbooks
    - "Old Homes" compiled by Helen Blair Lamar, 4 folders; original and acid-free copy (Box 2)
    - Pages from unbound scrapbooks, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Hanks Family
      - First Generation
        - Cyrus D. Hanks (1812-1890) (Box 2)
        - Caroline Colbeigh Hanks (1820-1900) (Box 2)
        - Harriet Hanks Peloubet (b. 1802), sister of Cyrus Hanks (Box 2)
        - Almeda Hanks Ward, sister of Cyrus Hanks (Box 2)
        - Almira Hanks Stout, sister of Cyrus Hanks (Box 2)
        - Oliver P. Hanks, brother of Cyrus Hanks (Box 2)
        - Orianna Hanks Bostwick (ca. 1816-1896), sister of Cyrus Hanks (Box 2)
      - Second Generation
        - Cyrus and Caroline Hanks Family Group Portrait (Box 2)
        - Ella Aurelia Hanks North Cole (1837-1917) and husband Myron D. Cole (Box 2)
        - Frances (Fannie) Matilda Hanks (1840-1877) and with her sister Harriet (Hattie) (Box 2)
        - Harriet Marion Hanks Potts Orchard (Hattie) (1848-1943) and husband Ruell Orchard (Box 2)
        - Mary Cornelia Hanks (1854-1922) (Box 2)
        - Howard Hanks (b. 1851), wife Emma, daughter Lulu Hanks Geisler (b. 1878) and son-in-law Charlie Geisler (Box 2)
        - Herbert Mortimer Hanks (1863-1951) (Box 2)
      - Cousins of the Hanks Family (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Hanks Family and Friends (Box 2)
    - Blair Family
      - First Generation
        - George Blair (1786-1869), and wife Rhoda Blackman Mann Blair (1790-1874), parents of Austin Blair (Box 3)
      - Second Generation
        - Austin Blair (1818-1894) (Box 3)
          (See also Oversize UAm)
        - Sarah Horton Ford Blair (1824-1897), wife of Austin Blair (Box 3)
      - Third Generation
        - George Horton Blair (1850-1904), wife Vienna Peck Blair and children Harriet, Charles A. and Flora Blair (Box 3)
        - Charles A. Blair (1854-1912) (Box 3)
        - University of Michigan Class of 1876 25th reunion, with Charles A. Blair, elected Treasurer, 1901 (Box 3)
        - Michigan Supreme Court Bench with Chief Justice Charles A. Blair 1909 (Box 3)
        - Group Portraits including Charles A. Blair (Box 3)
        - Charles A. and wife Effie North Blair camping 1895 (Box 3)
        - Franz Schubert Club Portraits; one includes Charles A. and Effie North Blair. (Box 3)
        - Effie North Blair (1861-1944), wife of Charles A. Blair (Box 3)
        - Effie North Blair with family members and pets (Box 3)
        - Fred Johnson Blair (1860-1943), wives Katharine Horton and Alice Rea Blair (Box 3)
        - Austin True Blair (1864-1944) and wife Kitty O'Brien Blair (Box 3)
      - Fourth Generation
        - George Fred Blair (1880-1955), son of Charles and Effie North Blair, with wife Lucie Chamberlain Blair (1883-1973) (Box 3)
        - Ella Louise Blair (1882-1886), daughter of Charles and Effie North Blair (Box 3)
        - Walter Guy Blair (1884-1886), son of Charles and Effie North Blair (Box 3)
        - Helen Blair Lamar (1898-1981), daughter of Charles and Effie North Blair, as a child and with her parents (Box 3)
        - Helen "Peachie" Blair Lamar as an adult and with her husband George "Jack" Lamar (Box 3)
        - George "Jack" Lamar (Box 3)
        - Vacation snapshots of "Jack" and Helen Blair Lamar (Box 3)
        - Friends of Helen Blair Lamar (Box 3)
        - Friends of "Jack" and Helen Blair Lamar (Box 3)
        - Nellie Austin Blair Greene (1882-1953), daughter of Fred J. and Katharine Horton Blair, and her husband Ernest C. Greene (Box 3)
      - Fifth Generation
        - Austin Benedict (b.1899) and John Montgomery Blair (1901-1967), sons of Austin True and Kitty O'Brien Blair (Box 3)
        - Lucie Chamberlain Blair Grandstaff (b.1906), daughter of George F. and Lucie Chamberlain Blair, with her sister Helen Louise Blair Clarke (b.1913) and her children (Box 3)
        - George F. Blair, Jr. (b. 1915), son of George F. and Lucie Chamberlain Blair (Box 3)
        - Barbara Lee Blair Matthews (b.1918), daughter of George F. and Lucie Chamberlain Blair, and her husband Guy Matthews and daughter Joan (Box 3)
        - Marjorie Greene, daughter of Nellie Blair and Ernest Greene, with her mother (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Blair Family Groups (Box 3)
      - Blair Family Groups at Portage Lake (Box 3)
      - George and Fred Blair's Florida Pineapple Plantations circa 1895 (Box 3)
      - Blair Family Houses and Pets (Box 3)
      - Named but unidentified Blair Family Members (Box 3)
      - Unidentified Blair Family Members (Box 3)
      - Lot V. North (1806-1900), grandfather of Effie North Blair, and his sister Lucy North (Box 3)
      - Guy F. North (1861-1944), father of Effie North Blair (Box 3)
      - Charles Hiram (b.1827) and Sophia Chase Horton, parents of Katharine Horton Blair, wife of Fred Johnson Blair (Box 3)
      - Heywood Family Group Portraits (Box 3)
      - Houses and Nature Views, primarily Michigan (Box 3)
      - Grammercy Park, New York City (Box 3)
      - President of Union College (Box 3)
  - Ambrotypes & Daguerreotypes
    - Cyrus D. and Caroline Colbeigh Hanks with a child identified as Jennie Hanks circa 1858, 1/4 plate cased ambrotype (Box 4)
    - Cyrus D. Hanks., 1/6 plate daguerreotype, heavily oxidized (Box 4)
      (possibly taken in Adrian, Michigan, 1859)
    - Harriet Hanks Peloubet (b.1802), sister of Cyrus D. Hanks, and her husband Chabrier Peloubet (enclosed note is incorrect) circa early 1840s, 1/6 plate cased daguerreotype (Box 4)
    - Chabrier Peloubet, husband of Harriet Hanks (b.1802)., 1/6 plate daguerreotype, original seal intact (Box 4)
    - William Hershey (1836-1857), given to Fannie Hanks (1840-1877), daughter of Cyrus and Caroline Hanks 1856, 1/9 plate cased ambrotype, backed with felt (Box 4)
    - Unidentified child circa early 1850s, 1/9 plate cased daguerreotype with original seal intact (Box 4)
      (with poem clipped from newspaper)
    - Unidentified woman circa late 1850s, 1/6 plate ambrotype, back has been lacquered (Box 4)
  - Tintypes
    - Guy Franklin North (ca. 1832-1890), father of Effie North Blair and trumpeter of Company B, 18th Michigan Infantry (1862-1865) circa 1862, 1/9 plate cased tintype, emulsion bubbling off tin (Box 4)
    - Hattie Hanks Potts Orchard (1848-1943), daughter of Cyrus and Caroline Hanks circa late 1870s, 1 long 1/9 plate and 1 1/6 plate (Box 4)
    - Fannie Hanks (1840-1877) and Jennie Hanks circa 1870s, Long 1/9 plate (Box 4)
    - Fannie Hanks or one of her sisters (enclosed note is incorrect) circa 1870s, Small cut plate (Box 4)
  - Glass Plate Negatives
    - The forks of the Grand River, taken from canoe 1896 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Center Lake looking east from canoe clubhouse 1896 (Box 4)
    - Camp in Chippewa County in construction 1899 (Box 4)
    - Camp in Chippewa County, Kitchen tent 1899 (Box 4)
    - Camp in Chippewa County, Sitting Room 1899 (Box 4)
    - Florida Plantations on the St. Lucie inlet
      - George Horton Blair's (1850-1904) place, 8 plates (Box 4)
      - Fred Johnson Blair's (1860-1943) place, 3 plates (Box 4)
      - Alice Rea Blair, Fred Johnson's wife, her sister Hattie and the Rea house in Florida, 3 plates (Box 4)
      - Pineapples and St. Lucie inlet, 2 plates broken (Box 4)
    - Portage Lake, where the Blairs had a summer cottage
      - Views of Portage Lake, 2 plates (Box 4)
      - Cottage at Portage Lake, 3 plates 1 broken (Box 4)
      - Welling's House 1897, 3 plates (Box 4)
      - Camp on Ready's Island, Portage Lake 1897, 5 plates (Box 4)
      - Picnicking at Portage Lake, 2 plates (Box 4)
      - Bathing and canoeing at Portage Lake 1897, 4 plates (Box 4)
      - Blair Family at Portage Lake, 8 plates 1 broken (Box 4)
    - Group shots with combinations of Blair, Welling, Hills, Gibson, Snow and Veeder 1897, 8 plates (Box 4)
    - Camp at Clark's Lake 1898, 3 plates (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous people, 4 plates (Box 4)
    - Badly deteriorated plates, 4 plates (Box 4)